Okay בוקר טוב Boker Tov today's דף daf is כ"ב עמוד א'
Kaf-Beit amud aleph כ"ב Kaf-Beit and we're going to continue about חנוכה.
Chanukah. I did want to spend one minute to mention the story
of חנוכה Chanukah quoted in the גמרא Gemara which is from מגילת
תענית. Megillat Ta'anit. This is a relatively recent volume on מגילת תענית
Megillat Ta'anit which is an academic volume which was done by Vered
Noam and really מגילת תענית Megillat Ta'anit as I told you is
extremely short. I will read you for example
all of מגילת תענית Megillat Ta'anit
here on חנוכה Chanukah yes but let me I mean the whole
thing is four pages here with a million footnotes.
So here's all of מגילת תענית Megillat Ta'anit on כסלו. Kislev. בתלתא
בכסליו אתנסון תמיסא מן דרתא Bi-tlata be-Kislev itnussun timusa min darta בשבעה
יום טבא bi-shiva yom tava ובעשרין וחד יום הר גריזים ve-appin va-achad
yom Har Gerizim ובעשרין וחמישה ביה חנוכה יומין תמניא דלא למספד u-va-esrim
ve-chamisha pucha Chanukah yomin tamnaya de-lo le-mispade ובעשרין ותמניא נטלו ba-esrim u-temanya
ne-itosei and then we're up to טבת. Tevet. Okay so anyway so
basically it's like extremely wait it's extremely short few words for the
four five days of each month that you cannot have a הספד
hesped with no explanation. Now very early on there was a gloss
on this which is called in scholarly language a scholion plural scholia.
Anyway which is the gloss. Now this gloss also is relatively early
probably end of the Tannaitic period and beginning of the גמרא Gemara
period and there are two very different versions one that seems to
be more from ארץ ישראל Eretz Yisrael one more from בבל. Bavel.
Now yesterday I told you that in error that this version of
you know the whole story about the חשמונאים Chashmonaim the scholion basically
gives the historic background to explain what these holidays are about on
all of the holidays of the מגילת תענית Megillat Ta'anit not just
on חנוכה Chanukah it's for the entire מגילת תענית. Megillat Ta'anit. So
I had assumed that the one here in the גמרא Gemara was
from this scholion because actually I had read a different edition of
מגילת תענית Megillat Ta'anit which had these lines in the גמרא Gemara
but actually the manuscripts of it show as I said basically two
different families neither of which has the version of the miracle of
the oil
and what we have currently as the gloss on מגילת תענית Megillat
Ta'anit is a hybrid of two the two early versions plus heavy
influence from the תלמוד בבלי Talmud Bavli and grafts from significant segments
of the תלמוד בבלי. Talmud Bavli. So the only source of miracle
of the oil is in the תלמוד בבלי Talmud Bavli and from
there it made its way into this gloss on מגילת תענית Megillat
Ta'anit but the actual two glosses of מגילת תענית Megillat Ta'anit both
try to explain why eight days but they don't talk about the
oil what they say why is it eight days when they did
the חנוכת המשכן Chanukat Hamishkan it was seven days and when they
did the חנוכת המזבח Chanukat Hamizbeach in the time you know of
the מקדש Mikdash in שלמה Shlomo it was seven days well whatever
but why is this eight days. So they say well because it
was eight days they were busy you know rededicating the מזבח mizbeach
and remaking a מנורה menorah and involving themselves with the lighting of
the מנורה. menorah. Nowhere does it say anything about the oil and
being טמא tamei and having to purify it. In one version it
actually says all of the כלים kelim were טמא tamei and therefore
what they had to do was they had to remake a מנורה
menorah and that actually is a story that is also found in
the בבלי Bavli how the first מנורה menorah they made when they
came into the בית המקדש Beit HaMikdash was they took their spears
and they covered their spears with like lead or something and that
was their initial מנורה. menorah. So that is one of the stories
but because the מנורה menorah was טמא tamei not because the vessels
were טמא. tamei. Anyway if people want to look at it afterwards
you can take a look because of the חשמונאים Chashmonaim whatever you
can look at it here but it is the בבלי Bavli that
has the one version about the oil and as I said you
know there's a very nice מהר"ל Maharal but he's bothered with this
and what's the whole yeah no and his basic explanation is yes
of course the primary miracle was about you know the war over
the Greeks and rededicating the מקדש Mikdash but the miracle of the
oil showed that it was God who was a part of that
whole process and it was about God's presence dwelling again with בני
ישראל Bnei Yisrael and that sort of a אגדתא aggadata that we're
going to see very soon. And as I said again yesterday some
want to tie that into whole idea of מהדרין מן המהדרין. mehadrin
min hamehadrin. Number one they want to explain either that you know
they didn't really need טהור tahor oil טומאה הותרה בציבור tumah hutra
betzibbur or maybe they could have gotten טהור tahor oil you know
some other way anyway but that because we went out of our
way to try to do it בטהרה betaharah even if it wasn't
really necessary so to sort of mimic that הידור hiddur the attempt
to do it you know the best possible way and to add
to that the מהר"ל's Maharal approach that God went out of his
way in order to show you know his involvement and his presence
and that the miracle involved in him so it's a really it's
a miracle in which it's a commemoration in which we have these
levels of
מהדרין mehadrin and
מהדרין מן המהדרין. mehadrin min hamehadrin.
I do not know that. I haven't read all, I mean it's
a, I haven't read all, I mean he has an extensive discussion
about it, but I think there's an assumption that it's, you know,
almost fully intact. Yeah, if not fully. Okay, so let's take a
look now back to the גמרא. Gemara. תנן התם. Tnan hatam. It
is six lines from the bottom on כ"א ע"ב. chaf aleph amud
bet. תנן התם. Tnan hatam.
We learned over there, this is a משנה Mishnah in בבא קמא.
Bava Kamma. הגץ היוצא מתחת הפטיש, Gitz hayotzei mitachat hapatish,
if a spark comes out from under the, like the hammer, ויצא
והזיק, veyatza vehizik,
and this spark lit somebody's, you know, somebody's walking into the iron
smith's store and the spark hit him or the spark flew out
into somebody's yard and it started a fire, חייב, chayav, you're obligated.
This is a משנה Mishnah in בבא קמא Bava Kamma that's dealing
with the obligations about fire, about אש, esh, one of the four
categories of your property that does damage. Now, גמל שטעון פשתן, gamal
sheta-un pishtan, if a camel is,
has flax on its back, is carrying flax, והוא עובר ברשות הרבים,
vehu over birshat harabim, and it's walking in the public domain, ונכנסה
פשתנו לתוך החנות. venichnesa pishtano letoch hachanut.
Now
you have overloaded it with flax because you're supposed to keep your,
you know, loads within the parameters of the public domain and here
it went ahead
and, I gotta just tell this joke. So these two guys are
driving a truck
and they come to a sign that says overpass, you know, what
is it, overpass, 18 feet height limit, whatever. So one looks at
the other and says, "See any cops?" So
anyway, so okay, so you're supposed to keep your flax within the
parameters of the רשות הרבים rishut harabim and you did not, you
overloaded your camel here. ונכנסה פשתנו לתוך החנות, venichnesa pishtano letoch hachanut,
so the flax therefore went into this guy's store where he had
a fire, a light lit, ודלקה בנר של חנווני, vedalaka bener shel
chanvani, and it was lit by the candle of the storekeeper, והדליקה
הבירה, vehidlikta habira,
and based on this, the flax caught on fire and then the
flax caught another building on fire, a huge building on fire, so
who's obligated? בעל הגמל חייב. ba-al hagamal chayav. Not only are you
the store owner exempt from hurting the flax or the camel, it's
really the owner of the camel's fire, he essentially added fuel to
the flame, was negligent, and he is now responsible for all damage
that the fire does. Okay, if you're intrigued by this, we will
get to בבא קמא Bava Kamma in about two years. הניח החנווני
נרו מבחוץ, hiniach hachanvani nero mibachutz,
now if the, however, storekeeper had his candle on the outside of
the store in the space which normally the people of רשות הרבים
rishut harabim are entitled to, then חנווני חייב, chanvani chayav, then it's
the store owner's fire and he's liable for any damage that is
incurred. רבי יהודה אומר, Rabbi Yehuda omer, now Rabbi Yehuda says, ah,
בנר חנוכה פטור, be-ner Chanukah patur, if it was a חנוכה Chanukah
candle he is exempt, because he's entitled to keep his חנוכה Chanukah
candles outside and presumably if you are walking in רשות הרבים rishut
harabim during חנוכה, Chanukah, you have to know to keep your stuff
a little bit more, a little bit more pulled in. Okay, or
it also could be issues about doing a מצוה mitzvah gives you
a certain level of exemption. Anyway, things to be worried about if
we're learning בבא קמא. Bava Kamma. אמר רבינא, Amar Ravina, said Ravina,
משמיה דרבא mishmei deRava or משום רבא, mishum Rava, זאת אומרת נר
חנוכה מצוה להניחה בתוך עשרה. zot omeret ner Chanukah mitzvah lehannicha betoch
asara.
This teaches you that you have to put the נר חנוכה ner
Chanukah within עשרה טפחים asarah tefachim off of the ground. Why? דאי
סלקא דעתך למעלה מעשרה, de-isalka da-itach lemala me-asara, if you're entitled to
put it higher than עשרה asara off of the ground, לימא ליה,
leima lei, לימא ליה היה לך להניחה למעלה מגמל ורוכבו. leima lei
haya lecha lehannicha lemala migamal verochvo.
So presumably there's an assumption that if it's higher than עשרה, asara
there's no greater height, like then it could be very, very high.
So he says, if you had no, you know, maximum height, then
the guy should have said, "Hey look, I know it's חנוכה, Chanukah,
but you know, there's the רשות הרבים rishut harabim and you know,
people are passing by, so put it very, very high, higher than
even a camel so that it's out of anybody's, you know, reach."
So he says no, ודילמא, vedilma, that maybe not, that maybe not
an argument. דילמא אי מטרחת ליה טובא אתי לאימנועי ממצוה. dilma im
matracha lei tuvah ati le-imnu-ei mimitzvah. Maybe we can't make that demand
on people. Maybe technically you're allowed to put it higher and you
could put it higher than a camel, but if we would insist
you would do it, you wouldn't bother doing the מצוה. mitzvah. So
we had to give you, recognizing that it's חנוכה Chanukah and people
want to do the מצוה, mitzvah, you know, we had to give
you as a store owner a certain amount of latitude that you
can put it in a convenient place. And once we've given you
the right to put it in a convenient place, it becomes the
responsibility of the people in רשות הרבים rishut harabim to take proper
heed. And this is a general question, you know, in בבא קמא,
Bava Kamma, primarily about areas of רשות הרבים. rishut harabim. You know,
if you have certain rights, who has the rights and who has
to pull back because of the rights? You fundamentally say, "I've got
a right to go in there with my, with my animals and
therefore you have to..." keep your food out of the way and
if your food is exposed and my animal eats it it's not
my problem that was your fault or do we say no you
have a right to have your food there and I gotta watch
my camel. So generally we say I've got a right to have
my animals and you have to be up on the you know
the responsible and aware of that of that right and therefore if
my animal damages with walking on things and eating things I'm exempt.
Okay but but fire is anyway a little bit different and so
here what it's saying is you might not be required to have
your חנוכה Chanukah candle that low but we might say you're not
you're allowed to because otherwise it would make it too difficult to
do the מצוה mitzvah and once we've allowed you to do that
then it becomes the people using רשות הרבים Reshut HaRabim to be
aware and to take caution and if they don't they become the
negligent party. Yes Rivka.
Why is he putting it in his store? Isn't it a מצוה
mitzvah to light it at home?
Oh that's a very good question you're right. So excellent question. So
you're right it is actually is not a מצוה mitzvah to light
it in a place of business if it is not your home.
This has to assume that his home is either his home also
serves as his store or and this would be a much bigger
חידוש chiddush from a בבא קמא Bava Kamma perspective that even if
they're just doing it in their store just you know for a
מנהג minhag like we light things in the שול shul for a
מנהג minhag and not technically for a מצוה mitzvah that is enough
to exempt him and to put the liability on the other. It
doesn't sound that way from the גמרא Gemara because the גמרא Gemara
speaks about whether it was a מצוה mitzvah to do it within
ten or not within ten and so on. So it's an excellent
question and it would and you would probably the simplest answer is
that his store is also his home but it is an excellent
question. Yes Jody.
We light in שול shul as מנהג minhag but we still say
a ברכה. bracha.
Yeah okay so that's a question on certain מנהגים minhagim you make
a ברכה bracha I can't get into that. I will say by
the way so now we're getting into the question of how high
so we're suggesting it has to be within ten we're saying not
necessarily you know but I but I will also say that as
a side comment the only place in the משניות Mishnayot that it
mentions חנוכה Chanukah is this one occurrence in בבא קמא Bava Kamma
as a complete four words בנר חנוכה פטור b'ner Chanukah patur whatever
בנר חנוכה פטור b'ner Chanukah patur three words parenthetical statement and so
on. So why is חנוכה Chanukah not appear in the משנה? Mishnah?
You have a whole מסכת masechet devoted to פורים Purim and מגילה
Megillah and so on. So the רמבן Ramban says it could be
that the rabbis were a little bit critical of the חשמונאים Chashmonaim
not for the נס חנוכה nes Chanukah but for afterwards having seized
the rulership and because you're normally supposed to separate כהונה kehunah and
religious authority from political authority and the political authority is supposed to
be בית דוד Beit David and so on. So he says that
maybe it was a whole critique of of you know of of
that phenomenon which is why it was not sort of made a
big deal in the משנה. Mishnah. That's at least what the רמבן
Ramban says whatever answer you give it is certainly worth noting this
is that the only occurrence of חנוכה Chanukah in the משנה. Mishnah.
Yes Michael.
You know if anything it seems to me that the מחשבה machshava
you have to put it more than ten not less than ten
because how tall is a גמל? gamal? Pretty tall. So this גמל
gamal what's laden with stuff...
Oh that's as I said the גמרא Gemara assumes that if it's
not if ten isn't a maximum then there's no maximum and if
there's no maximum then you would have put it higher.
But I understand but the משמעות mashma'ut of the case seems to
be that he did put it higher than ten because how'd the
גמל gamal manage to catch things on fire?
Oh that's an interesting point.
גמלים Gamals are pretty tall.
That's that's a good question. That's a good question. If it was
only ten טפחים tefachim high how does the גמל gamal imagine unless
it's really that the flax was like not just wide but falling
over the sides but that's a good point. Okay so let's take
a look now as the גמרא Gemara continues. אמר רב כהנא Amar
Rav Kahana דרש רב נתן בר מניומי משמיה דרבי תנחום darash Rav
Natan bar Minyomi mishmei d'Rabbi Tanchum סבר savar רב נתן בר מניומי
Rav Natan bar Minyomi expounded in the name of רב תנחום Rav
Tanchum דף כב עמוד א daf kaf bet amud alef נר של
חנוכה שהניחו למעלה מעשרים אמה ner shel Chanukah shehinicho lemala me'esrim amah
so we have said do you have to is it a מצוה
mitzvah it also doesn't say that it's פסול pasul otherwise but at
least we ask if there was an idea doing it within ten
טפחים. tefachim Now the normal now it's interesting when you think about
height the normal two heights in הלכה halacha that we tend to
pay attention to are ten טפחים tefachim. and then twenty אמה. amah.
Also that's true but okay after ג gimel טפחים tefachim and then
ten טפחים tefachim so ten טפחים tefachim is like three feet twenty
אמה amah is thirty feet okay so the first question is does
it have to be within three feet? Now he says if it's
higher than thirty feet if it's higher than twenty אמה amah then
פסולה pesula it is invalid. Why? כסוכה וכמבוי Kesukkah u'kemavoi because we
have a number of cases where we assume that things that are
higher than twenty feet high are not visible from the ground level.
You don't normally I mean you'd have to bend your neck a
lot to see it or you'd have to be a good distance
away to see it. So therefore if your סוכה sukkah is higher
than twenty אמה amah some say it's invalid because different reasons why
it's invalid but one explanation is because you won't naturally see the
סכך. s'chach. You'll know you're between walls but part of the core
of the סוכה sukkah is the סכך. s'chach. We also by a
מבוי mavoi well that's one approach. Also by you have to be
aware by a מבוי mavoi when you can have a beam for
the opening of the מבוי mavoi the fourth side that has no
wall if that beam is higher than twenty אמה amah you won't
see the beam and it won't serve its function to serve as
a היכר heker and to serve as a sign. So he's saying
the same about נר חנוכה. ner Chanukah. נר חנוכה, Ner Chanukah, if
it's higher than 20 אמות amot and you're walking in רשות הרבים,
Reshus Harabbim, you won't see it. So that of course creates problems
for people who live on second stories and whatever, where do they
put it? The גמרא Gemara actually said earlier that if you are,
if you're דר בעליה dar be'aliyah you put it in the חלון
הסמוכה לרשות הרבים, chalon hasemucha le-Reshus Harabbim, although there second stories were
probably not higher than 30 feet off the ground. What do we
do for us? So it's an interesting question. Again, we always fall
back on the possibility you're יוצא yotzei just for the people in
the house, but there are also contemporary realities. First of all, if
you're in Manhattan, then you see what your people across the apartment
across the street are doing. But also if you have wide streets
or whatever, sometimes there are, you get a good distance and it
is easy to see things that are higher, but it raises that
question about that application nowadays. Okay, now the גמרא Gemara continues. ואמר
רב כהנא דרש רב נתן בר מניומי משמיה דרבי תנחום. V'amar Rav
Kahana darash Rav Natan bar Minyumi mishmei de-Rabbi Tanchum. So the same
tradition here of רב כהנא Rav Kahana in the name of רב
נתן בר מניומי Rav Natan bar Minyumi in the name of רבי
תנחום. Rabbi Tanchum. מאי דכתיב, Mai de-chtiv, what is meant by the
verse והבור ריק אין בו מים? ve-habor reik ein bo mayim? Right,
this is from them throwing יוסף Yosef into the בור. bor. וישב,
Vayeshev, which is the פרשה parshah we always read on חנוכה. Chanukah.
Okay, so anyway that's an interesting connection. Anyway, what is it meant
when they said the pit that they threw him into was empty,
there was no water? ממשמע שנאמר והבור
ריק, Mimmashma shene'emar ve-habor reik, if it's empty, איני יודע שאין בו
מים, eini yodeia she-ein bo mayim, of course there's no water. אלא
מה תלמוד לומר אין בו מים, Ela mah talmud lomar ein bo
mayim, what does it mean there's no water? מים אין בו, Mayim
ein bo, there wasn't water, אבל נחשים ועקרבים יש בו, aval nechasim
va'akrabim yesh bo,
there were snakes and scorpions. Now, so that means they knew that
and they were trying to endanger his life? Or they didn't know
that, but it was to tell you that God saved them miraculously?
Okay, not exactly clear the message he's trying to give about this.
I will say a famous explanation, the תורה תמימה Torah Temimah quotes
it but I don't think he's the first that says it, is
to connect it again to the חנוכה Chanukah story to say that
maybe the pit was deeper than 20 אמות. amot. He tries to
argue that when it says you cast something down it means 20
אמות. amot. Not exactly clear where he's getting that from, but okay.
So if the pit was so deep, they thought there was nothing
in it, because remember it says ראובן Reuven was trying to save
him. So he wouldn't have put him with snakes and scorpions. So
they thought there was nothing in it, but really there was snakes
and scorpions. Why couldn't they see the snakes and scorpions? Because it
was 20 אמות amot away. So that shows you if things are
too high up or too low down, you're not going to see
it. Of course it's a little bit עיקר חסר מן הספר ikkar
chaseir min hasefer because it doesn't mention the 20 אמות amot in
that version.
What are the 20 אמות amot for?
That's also true. Okay, אמר רבה, Amar Rabbah, moving back to חנוכה.
Chanukah. אמר רבה נר חנוכה מצוה להניחה בטפח הסמוכה לפתח. Amar Rabbah
ner Chanukah mitzvah lehannichah be-tefach hasemucha le-fetach. So now
we're talking about how high, can't be higher than 20 אמות, amot,
עשרה asara, טפחים tefachim a little debated, although that's certainly the מצוה
לכתחילה. mitzvah lechatchilah. And then רבה Rabbah says you have to put
it in the טפח tefach near the doorway. Presumably this means that
you're by your doorway. Question if it means the door or the
actual doorway because sometimes there's a thickness of the door frame that
goes beyond the door. And then within one טפח tefach of that
towards the outside it has to be. So it has to be
pretty close to the doorway or else if it's too far people
won't know it's associated with your building and they won't know it's
yours and they won't see it as a נר חנוכה ner Chanukah
or certainly not as your נר חנוכה. ner Chanukah.
I'm sorry, בטפח הסמוכה לפתח, be-tefach hasemucha le-fetach, you're saying the inside
or the outside?
Outside, outside. Okay, but too far away it's in the middle of
the street. Okay, so it has to be within a טפח tefach
near your doorway, which is like three, four inches. והיכא מנח ליה,
Ve-heicha manach lei, which side you put it on? רב אחא בריה
דרבא אמר מימין, Rav Acha bereih de-Rabba amar mi-yamin, on the right.
Meaning if you're from the outside facing towards the in. רב שמואל
מדיפתי אמר משמאל, Rav Shmuel mi-Diphti amar mi-smol, on the left.
והלכתא, Ve-hilchata, it doesn't exactly explain what the debate is about, but
anyway והלכתא משמאל, ve-hilchata mi-smol, we rule on the left, כדי שתהא
נר חנוכה משמאל ומזוזה מימין. kedei she-tehei ner Chanukah mi-smol u-mezuzah mi-yamin.
So the מזוזה mezuzah is on the right as you walk in,
so this way you're surrounded by מצות. mitzvot. Presumably that's the opinion
that said on the right felt that the right always got preference
so you would have them both on the right. But we're saying
no, the preference is to have them one on each side. Okay,
and that's also how we rule. אמר רב יהודה אמר רב אסי.
Amar Rav Yehuda amar Rav Assi. So רב יהודה Rav Yehuda now
says in the name of רב אסי, Rav Assi, some say אמר
רב Amar Rav or
a question about the גירסא girsa there or maybe אמר רב ירמיה.
Amar Rav Yirmeya. אסור להרצות מעות. Assur le-hartzos ma'os. Now we get
into a very important discussion that seems to relate to the earlier
issue of can you derive benefit from נר חנוכה, ner Chanukah, but
does not make explicit reference to that. So let's see what it
says. אסור להרצות מעות, Assur le-hartzos ma'os, you cannot count money כנגד
נר חנוכה, keneged ner Chanukah,
in the presence of the
נר חנוכה. ner Chanukah. כי אמריתה קמיה דשמואל, Ki amritah kammeh de-Shmuel,
when I said this in front of שמואל, Shmuel, אמר, amar, so
שמואל Shmuel said, he responded this, וכי נר קדושה יש בה? Vechai
ner kedushah yesh bah? I don't get it. Does it have
קדושה? kedushah? If it's something that's sanctified to the בית המקדש Beis
Hamikdash you can't derive הנאה. hana'ah. But this isn't something sanctified, you're
using it for a מצוה. mitzvah. Like would you say
people twiddle with their ציצית. tzitzis. Can you say oh you can't
twiddle with your ציצית, tzitzis, can't do something, you can't I don't
know. scratch yourself with using your ציצית? tzitzis? Maybe it's a little
inappropriate, but whatever. So why can't you use the light of נר
חנוכה? ner chanukah? I don't understand. It doesn't have קדושה. kedusha. So,
מתקיף לה רב יוסף, maskif lah rav yosef, so רב יוסף rav
yosef said back, הכי דמי קדושה יש בו? hachi dami kedusha yesh
bo? I don't get it. So how about blood when you שוחט
shocht an animal and you have to cover the blood? Okay. Does
that כיסוי הדם? kisuy hadam? Does that when it's a חיה chayah
or a bird? We didn't, so not by like beef, so cows.
So does that have קדושה? kedusha? And nevertheless, we treat it in
a certain way. What does that mean? How do I see that?
דתניא, detanya, we taught in the ברייתא, braita, ושפך וכיסה, veshafach vechisah,
you shall spill the blood and cover it with dirt. במה ששפך
יכסה, bamah sheshafach yechaseh, you with what you spill the blood, your
hand which did the שחיטה, shechita, you use that to cover the
blood, the dirt, to cover the blood with dirt, meaning so you
know, you put dirt on with your hand or at least with
a shovel. But what do you not do? שלא יכסנו ברגל, shelo
yechasenu beregel, don't like kick the dirt over it with your foot,
which would be a very natural thing to do. שלא
יכסנו ברגל, shelo yechasenu beregel, why? שלא יהיו מצוות בזויות עליו, shelo
yehyu mitzvos buzuyos alav, מצוות mitzvos should not be sort of lowly
degraded in your eyes. You kick dirt over something, it's like you
know, it shows disregard. It shows that you don't respect it. So
you have to do it in a respectful way. Don't do it
in a non-respectful way. הכא נמי, hacha nami, שלא יהיו מצוות בזויות
עליו, shelo yehyu mitzvos buzuyos alav, here too, why do you not
count money by נר חנוכה? ner chanukah? That מצווה mitzvah should not
be, you know, that's not respectful. It's a disrespectful way. So I'm
not saying it has קדושה. kedusha. I'm not saying that, but I'm
saying you treat it in a respectful way and this is disrespectful.
Now I want to tell you that there's a lot of discussion
in the ראשונים rishonim about this. What exactly are the parameters? I
mean, the whole discussion isn't over. We're about to continue it in
a minute, but I just want to stop here for a second.
A, what exactly are the parameters? And B, how does it fit
into the earlier discussion where it was, you know, discussed whether
whether מותר להשתמש לאורה mutar l'hishtamesh l'orah and the גמרא gemara isn't,
whether you can use the light and the גמרא gemara seems to
be the same discussion, isn't bringing them in conversation. So what the
בעל המאור ba'al hama'or says is the following. He says the earlier
discussion, can you use the light? Remember רש"י rashi said the concern
there was if you use the light to do anything, it would
undermine the פרסום הנס. pirsum hanes. It wouldn't be obvious that it
was lit for the sake of the miracle, it would be for
the sake, you'd think for the light, and that's why you also
maybe need a שמש shamash and so on. That's what רש"י rashi
said. The בעל המאור ba'al hama'or has another approach. He says, no,
actually that approach that said אסור להשתמש לאורה assur l'hishtamesh l'orah actually
was saying that was saying that what do you call it? That
נר ner does קדושה יש בו. kedusha yesh bo. Not really, but
because as a certainly like borrowed a sense of the קדושה kedusha
from the מנורה. menora. Since it's all based on the מצווה mitzvah
of lighting of the מנורה, menora, like rabbinically we sort of give
it a quasi-קדושה, kedusha, we treat it as if it was the
lights of the מנורה menora and therefore you should not use the
light. That was the earlier discussion, not use light, actually give it
some type of rabbinic קדושה kedusha like the light of the מנורה.
menora. This discussion assumes that that's not true, that we don't say
it has קדושה kedusha and so on. And therefore generally you can
use it. The issue about counting the money was that counting the
money is considered to be בזויות. buzuyos. Like you know, it's like
it's a very mundane thing. As the way the בעל המאור ba'al
hama'or says, before we were talking about even doing מצוות mitzvos by
it. Learning, well learning by it if it's not שבת, shabbos, having
your שבת shabbos meal by it, using it in a מצווה mitzvah
context, that's not בזויות, buzuyos, but there was a question about הנאה.
hana'ah. Here, counting money, very mundane, that's בזויות buzuyos and therefore the
גמרא gemara says okay, this is a new problem. Maybe you're allowed
to use it for מצוות mitzvos but you shouldn't use it to
count your money, that's בזויות. buzuyos. That's how the בעל המאור ba'al
hama'or explains the two approaches. The רמב"ן ramban takes the opposite approach.
He says normally we understood you couldn't be משתמש לאורה mishtamesh l'orah
for something that was like an intensive use, because again, maybe like
רש"י rashi would undercut the מצווה. mitzvah. But counting money is like
it takes a few seconds, you're not sitting there and reading a
book by it. It takes two seconds, you just want to check
you know is this a 20 or a 10? or something like
that. So maybe that should be okay? And he says no, we're
out wanting any use, even a tiny little use, no use whatsoever.
So the response was no use whatsoever? Like that doesn't undermine its
the פרסום הנס. pirsum hanes. The only logic for that is that
you're treating it like it has קדושה, kedusha, like you can get
no הנאה, hana'ah, but that's not true. And then the רמב"ן ramban
understands that the answer of בזויות buzuyos is not to say that
this is a dead like you know, a denigrating act, because how
can you compare kicking dirt over something with counting money? Like you
know, if they're denigrating acts, they're not all the same. He says
he says what it means is in order to prevent you from
denigrating it, we treat it as if it has קדושה. kedusha. So
we get to the קדושה kedusha as a way of institutionalizing the
idea of not to denigrate it. So that sort of clear the
difference at the end of the day, if it was a little
complicated, at the end of the day, the בעל המאור ba'al hama'or
says that this issue here is just about using it for mundane
purposes and that's considered denigrating and the הלכה halacha is don't denigrate
נר חנוכה. Ner Chanukah. Don't do ביזיונות. bizuyot. The רמב"ן Ramban says
but you can have your שבת Shabbos light? The רמב"ן Ramban says
no. The point is in order so you shouldn't denigrate נר חנוכה,
Ner Chanukah, we're going to treat it as if it does have
קדושה. kedusha. So and therefore we're able to sort of say don't
use it for anything. Well yeah. Okay, so anyway just to be
aware that there's a lot of that discussion how to read this
and how to read the earlier סוגיא sugya and how to read
them in combination. Yes.
Well, because for פרסומי ניסא pirsumei nissa you should do everything you
could. Well no, they didn't use the מנורה Menorah of the בית
המקדש Beis HaMikdash for... no, meaning that's your thing about פרסומי ניסא
pirsumei nissa for the people in the house, but we're thinking about
פרסומי ניסא pirsumei nissa for the people outside. So they don't want
to see you using it, that seems like you just turned a
candelabrum, you know, because they didn't have electric lights, it could have
just been your light.
But these days, you know?
Okay, so fine.
We haven't changed anything.
All right. בעו מיניה מרבי יהושע בן לוי. Ba'ei minei mi'Rabbi Yehoshua
ben Levi. So now, that's one, that's one stopping point about ביזיונות
bizuyot and קדושה. kedusha. Now they ask the following question from רבי
יהושע בן לוי. Rabbi Yehoshua ben Levi. נוי סוכה מהו להסתפק ממנו
כל שבעה? Noi sukkah mahu lehistapek mimeno kol shiva?
Can you sort of take some of the things that you decorated
your סוכה sukkah with, particularly if you decorated them with fruit and
other types of edibles? Can you pull them off of your סוכה
sukkah during סוכות Sukkos if you're hungry? Okay? Can you pluck down
an apple? So is it okay or not? אמר ליה הרי אמרו
אסור להרצות מעות כנגד נר חנוכה. Amar lei harei amru assur lehartzos
ma'os keneged ner Chanukah. Look, you can't count money by the נר
חנוכה Ner Chanukah lights, that's considered inappropriate, ביזוי, bizuy, קדושה, kedusha, however
you explain it. So here too, you can't take it, you can't
use, you know,
the
נוי סוכה. noi sukkah. So אמר רב יוסף, amar Rav Yosef, מרי
דאברהם, Mari d'Avraham, God of Abraham! So which is like obviously like
an exclamation. תלי תניא בדלא תניא. Tali tanya bidla tanya. You're connecting,
you are making dependent something that is
from a תנא-ic Tanna source on something that is not a... I
mean meaning something, yeah, you are making dependent a תנא-ic Tanna source
on a non-תנא-ic Tanna source. The teaching of not counting money by
נר חנוכה Ner Chanukah was an אמורא-ic Amora teaching. The teaching that
you can't use the נוי סוכה noi sukkah as we're going to
see is a ברייתא, Braita, is a תנא-ic Tanna teaching. So you
don't say we know סוכה sukkah from חנוכה. Chanukah. No, סוכה sukkah
we learn from an earlier source, from a ברייתא. Braita. We know
חנוכה Chanukah from סוכה. sukkah. You got it all backwards. Where's the
ברייתא? Braita?
חנוכה לא תניא. Chanukah lo tanya. The חנוכה Chanukah was not in
a ברייתא. Braita. It was an אמורא-ic Amora source. תלי תניא בדלא
תניא. Tali tanya bidla tanya. I'm sorry. סוכה תניא. Sukkah tanya. סוכה
Sukkah was a ברייתא. Braita. חנוכה
לא תניא. Chanukah lo tanya. דתניא, Detanya, and here's where סוכה sukkah
is in a ברייתא.
Braita.
סיככה כהלכתה. Sichachah kehilchasah. If you put סכך sechach correctly on your
סוכה. sukkah. ועיטרה, Ve'itra, and then you sort of beautified it, בקרמיים,
bekarmeyim, רש"י Rashi says it means like
colored sheets. ובסדינין, Uvesadinin, other types of sheets, ומצויירין, Umetzuyarin, right, sort
of with designs. ותלה בה, Vetalah bah, you hung from the סכך,
sechach, אגוזין, egozin, אפרסקין, afarsekin, שקדים, shkedim, ורמונים, verimonim, all these different
types of nuts and pomegranates, ופרכילי ענבים Uparkilei anavim and grapes, ועטרות
של שבלים Ve'ataros shel shibolin and little bunches of wheat,
יינות, שמנים, Yeinos, shemanim, oils, presumably in some type of a container.
And wines and oils and flour. אסור להסתפק מהן. Assur lehistapek mehen.
So you have this נוי חנוכה, noi Chanukah, נוי סוכה, noi sukkah,
you cannot get hungry and take it down and eat it. כל
שבעה עד מוצאי יום טוב האחרון של חג. Kol shiva ad motzei
Yom Tov ha'acharon shel Chag. Until the last day, evening going through
שמיני עצרת. Shmini Atzeres. Because since you can't use it בין השמשות
bein hashmashos because it might still be סוכות, Sukkos, you can't use
it on שמיני עצרת Shmini Atzeres either. ואם התנה עליהן, Ve'im hisna
aleihen, however if you stipulated and you said, even though I'm putting
this up for נוי סוכה, noi sukkah, I'm not completely devoting it
for that purpose and I want to have the right to use
it anytime I want, then הכל לפי תנאו, hakol lefi tena'o, your
stipulation works. So anyway, we're not going to get into all these
issues about the stipulation, but the basic point is the basic teaching
is by סוכה. sukkah. So therefore, you should not say we learn
חנוכה Chanukah from סוכה. sukkah. I mean we learn סוכה sukkah from
חנוכה, Chanukah, we learn חנוכה Chanukah from סוכה. sukkah. So the גמרא
Gemara seems to accept it, but then says I'll do you one
better. אלא אמר רב יוסף, Ela amar Rav Yosef, אבוהון דכולהו דם.
avohon dekulhu dam. Actually, says רב יוסף, Rav Yosef, the core teaching,
right, the father of all of these is blood. From blood we
learn that the idea of מצוות ביזוי, mitzvos bizuy, and that leads
to the teaching about חנוכה Chanukah and the teaching about סוכה sukkah
about not using them for other purposes. Now, I do want to
point out that these are all different types of applications. One is
kicking dirt over something, the other is just using the light, and
by the סוכה sukkah issue it's actually
diverting it from its מצוה mitzvah purpose. You're taking it away from
serving... which is not true in the other cases, from serving its
מצוה mitzvah purpose and you're actually, you know, just eating it or
whatever. So it's a question how we can compare all of those.
What also makes it difference is that if anybody's ever learned מסכת
סוכה, Masechet Sukkah, you learn that one of... that there's a lot
of הלכות halachos apply to the סכך sechach and the נוי סכך.
noi sechach. Number one is it's really מוקצה muktzah on like יום
טוב, Yom Tov, you know, it's... מוקצה, muktza, the סכך s'chach and
the נוי סכך. noy s'chach. Even if the if something falls down,
it's מוקצה muktza on יום טוב. Yom Tov. So it has a
different type of status anyway. Number two is, the גמרא Gemara talks
about because it says because it says ועשית חג הסוכות להשם אלוקיך.
Vasita Chag HaSuccos L'Hashem Elokecha. Is that the right פסוק? pasuk? Anyway,
the פסוק pasuk that says that juxtaposes סוכה sukkah with God's name
and it says כשם שחל שם שמיים על החגיגה כך חל שם
שמיים על הסוכה או על הסכך. keshem shechal shem shamayim al hachagiga
kach chal shem shamayim al hasukkah v'al has'chach. חג הסוכות תעשה לך
שבעת ימים וגומר. Chag HaSuccos ta'aseh lecha shivas yamim v'goimer. Maybe.
Okay. I'm not remembering the exact פסוק. pasuk. Anyway, that it says
like there's a קדושה, kedusha, it actually says God's name descends upon
the סכך. s'chach. There's a קדושה kedusha to the סכך. s'chach. And
possibly and presumably and from certain גמרות Gemaras it sounds like there's
a קדושה kedusha to the נוי סוכה noy sukkah as well. So
it's like it's a completely different category. It has all of its
own parameters and it really is about קדושה kedusha there. So the
ראשונים Rishonim worry about sort of fixing all of those and making
these all the same. Is it about ביזוי מצוה? bizuy mitzvah? Is
it about קדושה? kedusha? What's it about? Just to tell you that
the רמב"ן Ramban has a solution. רמב"ן Ramban says the whole point
is how do we institutionalize the problem of ביזוי מצוה bizuy mitzvah
by treating it as if it has קדושה. kedusha. So therefore that's
why we talk about קדושה kedusha to the נוי סוכה noy sukkah
as well and talk about not using it and so on. We
treat it as if it has קדושה. kedusha. Okay.
That's why we don't throw out our לולב lulav and אתרוג.
esrog. Right. So but the point but the point is all of
this is only as while it is still doing the מצוה mitzvah
during the seven days of סוכות Succos while the נר חנוכה ner
Chanukah still burning. Once the מצוה mitzvah is over then it does
not have קדושה kedusha and in that way it's different. It's called
תשמישי קדושה. tashmishei kedusha. Things that were used as מצוה mitzvah objects
like a לולב, lulav, ציצית, tzitzis, נר חנוכה, ner Chanukah, סכך. s'chach.
Once the מצוה mitzvah is over they don't have קדושה kedusha even
if they had it during the time and they can be used
for other purposes or they can be thrown out if they're done
respectfully if it's not ביזוי מצוה bizuy mitzvah and very different from
things that have שם השם shem Hashem like תפילין tefillin and מזוזה
mezuzah and so on. But when they are being used for the
מצוה mitzvah then they're limits either ביזוי מצוה bizuy mitzvah or maybe
even this concept of קדושה kedusha and that defines itself in two
ways. One is don't don't divert it from the מצוה mitzvah like
take the סכך s'chach down and take the נוי סוכה noy sukkah
down and even if you're not diverting it maybe don't get הנאה
hana'ah from it or don't use it in a way that is
considered to be disrespectful and that's the issue about the counting of
the money. Yes. You had a question? Okay. Yeah. the
תנאי t'nai whatever. I'm not going to get to that right now.
איתמר. Itmar. רב אמר אין מדליקין מנר לנר. Rav amar ein madlikin
mi-ner l'ner. Now we get to another important issue which also somewhat
touches on using it. רב Rav says you cannot use one חנוכה
Chanukah candle to light the other one. Okay. You have to so
that obviously is going to lead to the role of a שמש.
shamash. Before we had the role of a שמש shamash based on
we can't
we can't derive benefit from the light okay and therefore if there's
a שמש shamash it makes it clear that we're not getting benefit
from the חנוכה Chanukah candles. Here it's a different issue about can
you light from one candle to the next and if you can't
then you need some other thing to be lighting the candles. שמואל
אמר מדליקין. Shmuel amar madlikin. You can once you have the first
thing lit then you can use it to light the others.
Now we're going to list a whole three series of debates of
רב Rav and שמואל Shmuel that are not connected but they're connected
because of how we rule by them. The general rule is we
rule by רב. Rav. In these three cases we rule like שמואל.
Shmuel. Okay. So here it is you actually technically can light from
candle to candle. רב אמר אין מתירין ציצית מבגד לבגד. Rav amar
ein matirin tzitzis mi-beged l'beged. You cannot remove ציצית tzitzis from one
garment to another. Now if the first garment is no longer usable
then yes you can and you can undo the ציצית tzitzis and
put it on another. But the issue here is the first garment
still is usable. And somewhat similar to the issue about you know
taking the נוי סוכה noy sukkah out you're removing you're unmitzvahfying you
know like like when a museum sells its paintings rather than saying
they sell it they have a fancy term they what is it
they de
de I know deaccession it deaccession it whatever
anyway so anyway you so you are demitzvahfying the first טלית tallis
even though you're coming to use the ציצית tzitzis for another one.
So it's not as bad as eating the apple from the סכך
s'chach but nevertheless is that a problem or not a problem? So
רב Rav says
because here in the end it see okay so תוספות Tosafot discusses
if it's חובת גברא chovat gavra חובת מנא. chovat mana. But anyway
here at least another garment is getting the status in its stead
so maybe that's okay. So רב Rav so anyway but yeah Michael
is correct you know if you פסקן pasken that the garment requires
ציצית tzitzis even if you're not wearing it then it raises serious
question how can you מבטל mevatel that. So תוספות Tosafot deals with
that issue okay and maybe it's according to the פשט pshat or
certain that it's not about the garment. Anyway תוספות Tosafot deals with
it. But anyway so therefore but for now we just focus on
the idea that you know that you are removing the מצוה mitzvah
from one object. So רב אמר אין מתירין ציצית מבגד לבגד. Rav
amar ein matirin tzitzis mi-beged l'beged. You cannot. שמואל אמר מתירין מבגד
לבגד. Shmuel amar matirin mi-beged l'beged. You can. רב אמר אין הלכה
כרבי שמעון בגרירה. Rav amar ein halacha k'Rabbi Shimon b'gerira. We do
not rule like רבי שמעון Rabbi Shimon by גרירה. gerira. This is
an extremely important שבת Shabbat הלכה, halacha, reminding us back that we're
talking about שבת, Shabbat, which is the classic case is: you want
to drag a bench from one side of your yard to the
other. Okay? You're just trying to get it to the other side
of your yard. But the question is: as you're dragging it on
שבת, Shabbat, maybe it'll make a furrow in the dirt. And that
would be a מלאכה. melacha. You can't make a furrow in the
dirt. It's either the making a furrow, which is the beginning of
planting, or maybe it's בונה, boneh, you're constructing some type of a
hole to be used. But you're not intending to do it, and
it's not necessarily going to be done. It might happen. So that's
called אינו מתכוין. aino mitkaven. You're not intending for it, and it
won't even necessarily happen. So there's a debate.
רבי שמעון Rabbi Shimon says fine, you don't have to worry that
it might happen; if it does happen, it's not your fault, and
it's not like you did a מלאכה. melacha. ורבי יהודה v'Rabbi Yehuda
says no, you're not allowed to do it because it might happen,
and then you'll have wound up doing a מלאכה, melacha, not intentionally,
but you've done a מלאכה. melacha. So this is a question of
אינו מתכוין aino mitkaven is allowed. Basically, if אינו מתכוין aino mitkaven
was אסור, assur, our שבת Shabbat would be so much more difficult
than it is right now. So anyway, and that's actually how רב
Rav ruled. רב Rav said we don't rule like רבי שמעון Rabbi
Shimon by dragging the bench, and as long as something might happen
even if you're not intending it but it might happen as a
result of what you're doing, you can't do it on
שבת. Shabbat. ושמואל אמר הלכה כרבי שמעון בגרירה, v'Shmuel amar halacha k'Rabbi
Shimon b'gerira, we rule like רבי שמעון Rabbi Shimon by the dragging
of the bench. אמר אביי, amar Abaye, said אביי, Abaye, כל
מילי דמר, kol mili d'mar, all aspects regarding the master רבה, Rabba,
who was אביי Abaye's teacher, עביד כרב, avid k'Rav, he would rule
like רב, Rav, לבר מהני תלת דעביד כשמואל, l'bar mihani tlata d'avid
k'Shmuel, these three he sided with שמואל: Shmuel: מדליקין נר לנר, madlikin
ner l'ner, you can light from one candle to the next on
חנוכה, Hanukkah, ומתירין מבגד לבגד, u'matirin mibeged libeged, you can move ציצית
tzitzit from one garment to the next, והלכה כרבי שמעון בגרירה, v'halacha
k'Rabbi Shimon b'gerira, and we rule like רבי שמעון Rabbi Shimon by
גרירה. gerira. And for some reason that it has to give you
the context of. דתניא, d'tanya, we taught in a ברייתא, Baraita, רבי
שמעון אומר, Rabbi Shimon omer, גורר אדם מטה כסא וספסל, gorer adam
mita kisse v'safsal, you can be dragging a bed, a chair, or
a bench from one side of the yard to the other, ובלבד
שלא יתכוין לעשות חריץ, u'belvad shelo yitkaven la'asot haritz, as long as
you're not intending to make a furrow. And we actually rule that
way, and if you're doing, you can do certain things on שבת
Shabbat even though something might happen. I mean imagine if we didn't
say that. You
couldn't walk in certain mud because you'll be, or snow, soft dirt.
I mean whatever, there'd be a million things you couldn't do if
we didn't rule that way. Okay, now we're going to focus though
on the נר לנר. ner l'ner. יתיב ההוא מרבנן קמי דרב אדא
בר אהבה, yativ hahu meirabanan kamei d'Rav Adda bar Ahava, one of
the rabbis was sitting, meaning rabbinic student, in front of רב אדא
בר אהבה, Rav Adda bar Ahava, יתיב וקאמר, yativ v'ka'amar, and he
was coming and he was explicating what this debate was about, about
נר לנר. ner l'ner. טעמא דרב משום ביזוי מצוה. ta'ama d'Rav mishum
bizuy mitzvah. The reason of רב, Rav, like echoing what we just
said, is because it's not respectful for the מצוה. mitzvah. Now that's
a little bit funny. It's one thing to count money, it's another
thing to use one candle to light the other candle. Why is
that not respectful? So we'll see in a minute. אמר להו, amar
lehu, so he said to them, to the other rabbis presumably, לא
תציטו ליה, lo titzitu lei, don't listen to that. That, you know
they say there's no such thing as a bad question but whatever
bad idea, whatever, so he said, no, don't listen to him, that
was a bad suggestion. טעמא דרב משום דקא מכחיש מצוה. ta'ama d'Rav
mishum d'ka machish mitzvah. The reason of רב Rav is that you
are depleting the מצוה. mitzvah. Now not literally, but the way רש"י
Rashi explains it, not literally, but it looks that way. When you
take the light from one to the other, it looks like you're
somehow removing light from one candle and giving it to the other.
So it looks like you're sort of doing an incursion into the
other candle. It does sound a little bit. It does, yeah, it
does sound a little bit. But anyway, that's what he says. That's
because it looks like you're taking away. So the גמרא Gemara says
מאי
בינייהו, mai beinaihu, what would be a difference that would emerge from
these two approaches? איכא בינייהו דקא מדליק משרגא לשרגא. ika beinaihu d'ka
madlik mishraga l'shraga. They're not doing it through a middle thing. It's
not like you're
taking a stick and lighting from candle A, getting the stick on
fire, and then lighting candle B. What you're actually doing is you're
going directly from A to B. Okay? מאן דאמר משום ביזוי מצוה,
man d'amar mishum bizuy mitzvah, if it's because it's denigrating, so משרגא
לשרגא מדליק, mishraga l'shraga madlik, that's okay. It's only denigrating like, like
we said before, why is it denigrating if you're using one נר
חנוכה ner Hanukkah to light another נר חנוכה? ner Hanukkah? You're doing
another נר חנוכה ner Hanukkah מצוה mitzvah with it. Ah, but if
first you're lighting the, if you're taking a match to the נר
חנוכה, ner Hanukkah, then the first, what you're doing is you're first
lighting something that is not a מצוה. mitzvah. It's true the goal
is to do a מצוה, mitzvah, to use it to light another
candle, but the immediate act is you're putting a match to נר
חנוכה. ner Hanukkah.
That's considered something else, then use the match, and then from the
נר חנוכה ner Hanukkah you did that, so that's the problem.
Yes, correct. So therefore that would be the ביזוי מצוה. bizuy mitzvah.
Directly would not, but through a medium that would be not respectful
because the immediate act it's doing is not doing a מצוה, mitzvah,
it's lighting a match when you go put the match to one
of the נר חנוכה. ner Hanukkah. But מאן דאמר משום אכחושי מצוה,
man d'amar mishum ach-hushei mitzvah, if it's because of depleting the מצוה,
mitzvah, משרגא לשרגא נמי אסור, mishraga l'shraga nami assur, even from one
to the other it looks
like. Is better through an intermediary? No, that's also bad. They're both
bad.
Then what would you do?
Nothing, you'd have to use a שמש. shamash.
No, but then why wouldn't someone say, oh, he lit a נר
חנוכה ner Chanukah and now he's lighting his שמש shamash with a
נר חנוכה? ner Chanukah? No.
The שמש, shamash, no, the שמש shamash lights נר ner one, נר
ner two like we do.
But how do you, but someone's walking in, how do they know
that maybe you used this other candle?
That would not, that would not concern. We're not saying you're misinterpreting,
that we're not doing. It's what it looks like, not how it's
misinterpreted. Okay, מתיב רב אויא, maseiv Rav Avya, Rav Avya asks: סלע
של מעשר שני. sela shel ma'aser sheni. You have a coin of
מעשר שני. ma'aser sheni. If you have מעשר שני, ma'aser sheni, right,
every third and sixth year, a second tithe would go and be
brought to ירושלים. Yerushalayim. That could be a lot that you'd have
to schlepp to ירושלים, Yerushalayim, so you could transfer the קדושה kedusha
to money and bring the money to ירושלים. Yerushalayim. That money has
קדושת מעשר שני. kedushas ma'aser sheni. So you have a coin of
מעשר שני. ma'aser sheni. Now, אין שוקלין כנגדו דינרי זהב. ein shoklin
kenegdo dinarei zahav. You have a balance scale. You want to weigh
other gold דינרים dinarim to determine their weight and you're going to,
and you're using this as a counterweight. So that's using something with
real קדושה kedusha for a mundane purpose. That's obviously not acceptable. ואפילו
לחלל עליו מעשר שני אחר. ve'afilu lechalel alav ma'aser sheni acher. But
you know what you can't do? You can't even do it even
if the reason you're weighing the other gold coins is to use
them to redeem other מעשר שני. ma'aser sheni. So this is a
very analogous case. You're using מעשר שני, ma'aser sheni, it's through what
is now a mundane medium, a mundane intermediary, the gold coins that
don't have קדושה, kedusha, but the goal is to redeem other מעשר
שני. ma'aser sheni. So it's like putting your match to the candle
in order to light another candle. And here it says you can't
do it. Now, you might want to make a distinction. Here it
has קדושה. kedusha. That was the whole question. נר חנוכה ner Chanukah
doesn't have קדושה, kedusha, although maybe according to the רמב"ן Ramban it
does at the end. Anyway, the גמרא Gemara makes the analogy. So
let's take a look.
אי אמרת בשלמא דפליגי רב ושמואל מנר לנר. ee amrat bishlama d'paligi
Rav u'Shmuel miner l'ner. If you say that the debate of רב
Rav and שמואל Shmuel is direct from one candle to the next
because of it looks like, you know, because of it looks like
you're depleting, אבל בקינצא aval be'kinsa where you to use a, like
a, like a קינצא, kinsa, like a, not a twig, a match,
I'm saying a match, but a קינצא kinsa is like a, what
do you call it? A sliver of wood. Wood chip, splinter, whatever,
anyway, wood chip. אסור, assur, it's forbidden. So everybody would agree. If
you say everybody agrees going through an intermediary is forbidden, it's ביזוי
מצוה. bizui mitzvah. So then that works. הלא תהא תיובתא, halo tehei
tiuvta, it's not a contradiction. Because here we see by מעשר שני
ma'aser sheni going through an intermediary is no good. And similarly we
would say that by the נר חנוכה ner Chanukah going through an
intermediary would be no good. And they would only debate about doing
it directly. That makes sense. אלא אי אמרת בקינצא נמי שרי. ella
ee amrat be'kinsa nami shari. But if you say that שמואל Shmuel
allows even with a twig in the middle or whatever a, a
match in the middle, even going through an intermediary. הא תהא תיובתא.
ha tehei tiuvta. Why is it okay by נר חנוכה ner Chanukah
and not okay by מעשר שני? ma'aser sheni? Same idea. You're going
through the intermediary of the gold coins to get to מעשר שני.
ma'aser sheni. Going through the intermediary of the match to get to
another נר חנוכה. ner Chanukah. If it's okay by נר חנוכה, ner
Chanukah, why is it not okay by מעשר שני? ma'aser sheni? Again,
you could of course say that מעשר שני ma'aser sheni has קדושה,
kedusha, but let's see what the גמרא Gemara answers. אמר רבא גזרה
שמא לא יכוין משקולותיו וכמפקי להו לחולין. amar Rava gezira shema lo
yechawein mishkolosav vechamapki lehu lechullin. Here's the concern. Maybe you're going to
put, you're doing a counterweight, you need, you know, a hundred dollars
of gold coins in order to redeem the מעשר שני. ma'aser sheni.
You put your gold coins on the scale and it's too much
or it's too little. So you say okay forget it, I'm not
going to use these gold coins. I'll find, I'll go get my
silver coins, I'll go get different coins or whatever. So then what
will happen? Then you will have not in the end used it
towards מעשר שני. ma'aser sheni. So because you're weighing to determine, there's
a good possible outcome that in the end it won't be used.
And that's the problem. But in the case of the match, you
could also say the match might blow out, but still it's not
as likely. And in the case of the match, since it's almost
definitely going to go towards lighting another נר חנוכה, ner Chanukah, that's
a more reliable case and therefore that's okay. So that's how we
get out of that. Again, interesting because it also could have pointed
to the קדושה kedusha element, but that gets to the earlier discussion
about קדושה kedusha by נר חנוכה. ner Chanukah. Okay, so we're still
open whether they're debating everybody agrees an intermediary is no good, or
whether no, they're debating using the intermediary, even that might be okay.
מתיב רב ששת, maseiv Rav Sheshes, asks Rav Sheshes. And here again,
interestingly bringing in the מנורה menorah to the discussion of נר חנוכה,
ner Chanukah, at least for an analogy. מחוץ לפרוכת העדות יערוך, michutz
laparoches ha'eidus yaaroch, outside of the, you know, curtain of the testimony,
meaning the where the, you know, קודש קדשים, kodesh kodashim, Aaron shall
light the מנורה. menorah. וכי לא. vechilo. Does God need the light
of the מנורה Menorah *Menorah*? Why are we lighting the מנורה Menorah.
*Menorah*? Does God need it? Some say the question is, does Aaron
need it? But okay, we'll read it the more accepted way. Does
God need that? Why are we lighting the מנורה Menorah *Menorah*? But
ולא כל ארבעים שנה שהלכו בני ישראל במדבר לא lo. הלכו אלא
לאורו *v'lo kol arba'im shana shehalchu b'nei Yisrael bamidbar lo halchu ela
l'oro*? For 40 years they were being led by God's light. So
what does God need our light for? We need God's light. So
אלא *ela*, so what's the point of lighting the מנורה Menorah *Menorah*?
אלא עדות היא לבאי עולם *ela edut hi l'va'ei olam*, it is
a testimony to all people who come שהשכינה שורה בישראל *shehashchina shara
b'Yisrael*, that the divine presence dwells within Israel. So here notice and
this very ties into the point I said yesterday, beginning of today,
that the חז"ל *Chazal* see the light of the מנורה Menorah *Menorah*
as symbolizing God's presence. And therefore, you know, the significance of the
lighting of the מנורה Menorah *Menorah* when they are doing the חנוכת
המזבח *chanukat hamizbeach*, the חנוכת המקדש *chanukat hamikdash* at the time of
חנוכה Chanukah. *Chanukah*, and doing it בטהרה *betaharah*, the whole idea was
getting rid of not only the literal טומאה *tumah*, the figurative טומאה
*tumah* that was introduced by, you know, the Greeks and the idols
and all of that, and making it a place where now you
could once again have God's presence dwell. So the lighting of the
מנורה *Menorah* was extremely, could be symbolically significant about that. So you
really understand the power of the נס *nes* of the נר חנוכה
Ner Chanukah? *Ner Chanukah*, or focusing on the נס *nes* of נר
חנוכה Ner Chanukah. *Ner Chanukah*, if this is what is telling us
we have done a good job, we have cleaned it out, we
have made it once again a place fit for God's presence, you
know, when they dedicated the משכן *Mishkan*, you had a fire coming
down from heaven. Okay, you know, but what happened here to show
the, you know, that God was once again dwelling his presence in
the מקדש *Mikdash*. So, you know, understanding that that's like the problem
here, that how do they know even after everything they've done that
they've succeeded and once again it's a place of God's presence? Now
you understand the idea of focusing on this נס *nes*. It's not
just a נס *nes*, oh, wasn't that wonderful, eight days. It was
really a thing of way of God demonstrating that he was dwelling
the presence, that God's presence was once again dwelling in the מקדש
*Mikdash*. So anyway, that's a little, the גמרא Gemara *Gemara* doesn't say
that, but the גמרא Gemara *Gemara* speaks about it as God's presence,
and I think if you make the connection to חנוכה *Chanukah*, and
again this is along the lines of what the מהר"ל *Maharal* says,
you really understand the power of speaking about the נס חנוכה *nes
Chanukah*. Now back to our point. Okay, so what was the point,
anyway, how's this relevant to our halachic discussion? אמר רב Rav *Amar
Rav*, so said רב Rav *Rav*, what is the, מאי עדות *mai
edut*? Okay, I mean, I said it's symbolic, but it said it's
testimony, means it proves it. How, where does it prove God's presence?
So there was a נס *nes*, it's going to say, you know
what, there was a נס *nes* every day by the מנורה *Menorah*,
not just by חנוכה *Chanukah*. אמר רב זו נר מערבי Ner Maaravi,
*Amar Rav zo ner maaravi*, the western
lamp, you know, sort of light of the מנורה *Menorah*, שנותן בה
שמן כמדת חברותיה *she-noten bah shemen k'midat chavroteha*, it had the equal
amount of oil as all of the other, you know, lamps, branches
of the candelabra, וממנה היה מדליק ובה היה מסיים Uvah Hayah Mesayem
*u-mimena hayah madlik u-bah hayah mesayem*. You would light from it and
you would end with it. What does that mean? So what it
means is you had the branches of the מנורה *Menorah*, let's just
say five, I don't have seven fingers on my hand, but let's
assume these are three and three. Now which is the נר מערבי
Ner Maaravi *ner maaravi*? Interestingly, there's a debate whether the מנורה *Menorah*
was situated east-west, okay, and then, so then you'd assume the נר
מערבי Ner Maaravi *ner maaravi* is the most westernmost. But somewhat ironically,
we would say, no, the נר מערבי Ner Maaravi *ner maaravi* is
the first one that's west, meaning so it's the second candle from
the east, right? Because it's, first easternmost is in the east, that's
a little strange. Let's talk about the common perception, which is that
it was situated north-south, and the western one was the middle one
that was sort of pointing towards the קודש קדשים *Kodesh Kadashim*, right?
That's I think how we normally imagine it. And the others were
going in. Whatever it was, that was the one that was the
focal one, that נר מערבי Ner Maaravi *ner maaravi*. So what happened?
At night you would fill them up all with oil. Okay, you
would come back the next morning and they would have burnt out.
Now maybe some of them wouldn't because they had enough oil to
last the long nights of the winter. So if it was a
summer night, they would still be burning a little bit into the
day. But anyway, but even if they were all burnt out, the
נר מערבי *ner maaravi* through a miracle would still be burning. And
according to, now again, a certain ברייתא *braita* says they only had
the miracle certain times and other times they had to relight it
from the מזבח Mizbeach. *mizbeach*. But when there was this miracle, it
was still burning and it would remain burning until nighttime. It would
last 24 hours even though the other ones would go out early
at the end. And then, so the other ones in the morning
you would clean out and put in new oil and put in
new wicks. The נר מערבי *ner maaravi* would continue burning and only
at night would you then clean it out, new oil, new wicks.
And then you would light from the נר מערבי *ner maaravi*, which
had been still been lit, you would light from its wick, its
new wick, the old wick of the נר מערבי *ner maaravi* the
new wick, and then you'd use the new נר מערבי *ner maaravi*
to light all the others.
Hold on, did you light, you didn't light twice?
You only
lit in the night. Yeah. You lit in the night. You had,
well, in the day... So, let's say, you replace their oil and
their wicks. The נר מערבי, but you didn't light them. You only
light them at night. The רמב"ם Rambam says you lit in the
day as well. Okay, but all the other ראשונים Rishonim assume you
lit only right before nightfall. No, no, no. So therefore, comes the
night and the only thing still burning is the נר מערבי, everything
else has been cleaned out, you take out the wick, you clean
it out, you put in more oil, you put in a wick,
you use the old wick to light the new wick, and then
you use the new נר מערבי to light the others. Okay, so
that is the testimony which is that the miracle that occurred every
day that the נר מערבי lasted the entire 24 hours.
Well, the רמב"ם Rambam says
it
lasted a few minutes longer, right? It's written here.
Yeah, it's not in any biblical source, it's a rabbinic source.
It's a rabbinic source and the מנורה was indoors.
Yes, well, it was under a roof. No, it was under a
roof, it was in the היכל. Heichal. It was under a roof,
it was not exposed to air. There was a roof, there was
four walls.
Okay, but until the days of עזרא הסופר Ezra HaSofer or something,
and
then right, there was a time when the miracle stopped and they
had to use the fire from the מזבח. But anyway, there was
a period when there was this miracle. And again, as I said,
the significance about thinking about that, about שכינה שורה Shechinah Shoreh as
the miracle of חנוכה. Anyway, back to this point. So ממנה היה
מדליק, Mimmenah Hayah Madlik, the way רש"י Rashi reads it, תוספות Tosafot
varies a little bit, I won't get into it, but the way
רש"י Rashi reads it is they would light from it at night.
ובה היה מסיים and it was the very last thing that they
would clean out and change the oil, because they would only do
that right at the end of the day, where all the other
ones they would clean and change the oil at the first thing
in the morning. Okay, anyway, that's the testimony. But our point for
all of this is that they would use the נר מערבי to
light the other
lamps, the other, you know, parts of the מנורה. So the גמרא
Gemara says, והכא דכיון דקבי נרות, Vahacha Dekivan Dekavi Neirot, now the
גמרא Gemara says look, the נרות Neirot were fixed, you cannot remove
the lamp and take the little, you know, the little lamp part
off of the arm of the candelabrum and bring it to the
other, light the other lamps. The lamp part of the candelabrum was
fixed on the arm. So since it was fixed on the arm,
ושדי דלאו למשכא ואדלוקי, Vesaday De-lo-leimshek Veadlukei, so, you know, it's not
possible for you to remove it and
light. So the only way you could light from the נר מערבי
to the other ones was through a match, an intermediary. So here
it seems like if in the מנורה itself you were allowed to
light through an intermediary, how could there be any debate by
נר חנוכה? Ner Chanukah So the גמרא Gemara says, קשיא בין למאן
דאמר משום ביזוי מצוה בין למאן דאמר משום אכחושי מצוה. Kashya Bein
Leman De-amar Mishum Bizuy Mitzvah Bein Leman De-amar Mishum Ichshushay Mitzvah. Whichever
approach you say, at least there's one, at least one version, רב
at least is saying you can't go through an intermediary and maybe
even according to one version שמואל Shmuel is saying that and here
by the מנורה it's clear that you did go through an intermediary.
So the גמרא Gemara says, תרגמה רב פפא בפתילות הארוכות, Targumah Rav
Pappa Befitilas Ha-aruchos, like Michael said, they had really, really long wicks.
Okay, so you could just stretch the wick all the way to
the other. Fine. That works if you say that going direct is
okay, but there's still a version that רב says even going direct
is no good. The גמרא Gemara says, סוף סוף למאן דאמר משום
אכחושי מצוה קשיא, Sof Sof Leman De-amar Mishum Ichshushay Mitzvah Kashya, according
to the approach that the debate is that it looks like you're
depleting the מצוה Mitzvah and even going direct is no good, it's
a problem because by the מנורה you would go directly. So the
גמרא Gemara says, קשיא. Kashya. Okay, it's difficult. So for whatever reason
the מנורה was different, I don't know, but I'm still saying you
can't do it by נר חנוכה. Ner Chanukah: Okay, so but of
course that is a serious question. מאי הוי עלה. Mai Hava Alah.
Now interesting, you know, when the גמרא Gemara says תיובתא, Tyuvta, תיובתא
Tyuvta
means like complete contradiction, although every now and then we even rule
like something that we said תיובתא Tyuvta and then the גמרא Gmara
says תיובתא והלכתא, Tyuvta Vehilchasa, but קשיא Kashya we know means it's
a question but you don't, you know, it's not a knockout punch,
it's possible that it doesn't seal the deal. So the גמרא now
says, okay, what was the conclusion of all of this? Meaning, even
if we assume we rule like שמואל, Shmuel, again we want to
know, is it when you're going directly or even through an intermediary?
What's the story? So let's take a look. מאי הוי עלה, Mai
Hava Alah, what was the
upshot? אמר רב הונא בריה דרב יהושע חזינא. Amar Rav Huna Bereih
De-rav Yehoshua Hazina. Well, let's think about it, let's look, maybe that's
a little play on words. Okay, anyway, let's see. אי הדלקה עושה
מצוה, Ee Hadlakah Osah Mitzvah, if the act of מצוה Mitzvah is
done by the act of lighting, מדליקין מנר לנר, Madlikin Mi-ner Le-ner,
then it would be okay to go from one to the other.
Why? Because then you know you can't call that a ביזוי מצוה,
Bizuy Mitzvah, you're using it directly in an act of a מצוה,
Mitzvah, the act of lighting. אי הנחה עושה מצוה, Ee Hanachah Osah
Mitzvah, however if the מצוה Mitzvah isn't lighting but it's putting it
down, very interesting that the מצוה Mitzvah in נר חנוכה Ner Chanukah
would be putting it down, we'll see about that in a minute,
אין מדליקין מנר לנר. Ein Madlikin Mi-ner Le-ner. then you cannot because
then the act of lighting is itself not an act of a
מצוה, mitzvah, it's a way to get to the מצוה. mitzvah. The
מצוה mitzvah would be a stage later when you put it down.
Okay. Now, as תוספות Tosfos points out, this really doesn't focus on
the issue so much about אחושי מצוה, achushei mitzvah, it focuses more
on the idea about ביזוי מצוה bizuy mitzvah and so on, so
there's a little bit of a question about how this exactly fits
into the issue we were raising before. But it serves as a
nice segue to get us into this more interesting abstract debate about
what is the מצוה mitzvah of נר חנוכה: the act of lighting
or the act of putting it down? So for now we'll just
recognize that the more you emphasize the act of lighting, therefore the
less you'll have a problem of lighting from one candle to the
next, either directly or through an intermediary, because it's all a מעשה
מצוה. ma'aseh mitzvah. But if it's just getting you a step prior
to the act of the מצוה, mitzvah, those things become more problematic.
The basic הלכה halacha though seems to be just to know that
it seems to be that we rule מדליקין מנר לנר madlikin mi'ner
l'ner like שמואל Shmuel and even presumably through an intermediary, which raises
the question about why you need a שמש. shamash. So maybe that's
for the other reason, that it should be obvious you're not using
it for the light and so on. Even with all of that,
the מנהג minhag and already said by תוספות Tosfos is clearly that
אין מדליקין מנר לנר ein madlikin mi'ner l'ner even if according to
the הלכה, halacha, right, it seems like you should be allowed to.
Let's now turn to this issue about what makes the מצוה. mitzvah.
דאיבעיא להו, d'ibaia lei, oh, because the question was raised, דאיבעיא להו:
d'ibaia lei: הדלקה עושה מצוה או הנחה עושה מצוה? hadlakah oseh mitzvah
o hanacha oseh mitzvah?
Is the מצוה mitzvah done through lighting or through putting it down?
I'm going to qualify that in a minute but let's just get
started. תא שמע דאמר רבא: ta shma d'amar Rava: היה תפוס נר
חנוכה ועומד לא עשה ולא
כלום. haya tofus ner Chanukah v'omed lo asah v'lo klum. If you
were holding your נר חנוכה and you lit it while you were
holding a candelabra, you didn't do the מצוה. mitzvah. So that sounds
because it's not been put down. שמע מינה הנחה עושה מצוה: shma
mina hanacha oseh mitzvah: it's about putting it down, not about lighting
it. לא. התם הרואה אומר לצורכו הוא דנקיט ליה. hasam haro'eh omer
l'tzarcho hu d'nakit lei. No, even if it's the act of lighting,
that's not a good lighting when you're holding it. Why is it
not a good lighting when you're holding it? Because it looks like
why do you hold a candelabra? Because you're going to be walking
around in a dark room. It's a flashlight. So when you're holding
it, it does not do the purpose of פרסומי ניסא. pirsumei nisa.
So it was not because it wasn't put down, it was because
it was in a position that the act of lighting wasn't a
meaningful act of lighting. תא שמע. ta shma. So let's try again.
דאמר רבא, d'amar Rava, רבא Rava says: הדליקה בפנים והוציאה
לא עשה ולא כלום. hidlikah bifnim v'hotzia lo asah v'lo klum. If
you lit it inside, remember this was when the מצוה mitzvah had
to be done on the outside, not inside, and afterwards you brought
it outside, you didn't fulfill your obligation. It's worthless. Okay. So אי
אמרת בשלמא הדלקה עושה מצוה, ee amrat bishlama hadlakah oseh mitzvah, if
the act of the מצוה mitzvah is the act of lighting, הדלקה
במקומה בעינן, hadlakah bimkomah bainan, so you didn't do the act of
the מצוה. mitzvah. You lit it indoors and the act has to
be done outdoors. Outdoors is where you have your menorah. אלא אי
אמרת ela ee amrat לא עשה ולא כלום? lo asah v'lo klum?
אלא אי אמרת הנחה עושה
מצוה, ela ee amrat hanacha oseh mitzvah, if the whole idea is
putting it down after you lit it, so אמאי לא עשה ולא
כלום? amai lo asah v'lo klum? What do you mean? This should
be perfect. Why is it a problem? You lit it indoors and
then you did the מצוה mitzvah by putting it down outdoors. So
the גמרא says no, התם נמי הרואה אומר לצורכו הוא דאדלקה. hasam
nami haro'eh omer l'tzarcho hu d'adlakah. The problem is that when you
were walking with it from indoors to outdoors, it also looked like
you were using it as a flashlight. So you have to, it's
also a putting
down, it has to be a putting down that doesn't problematize what
it's about. So you have to light it outdoors and put it
down outdoors. But if you're carrying it and walking with it, then
it becomes very confusing. So we will continue with this debate tomorrow
and I will continue and I will want more sort of also
qualify or describe what at a deeper level this debate is about.